<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The substance of a letter occasioned by a discourse of the time called Christmas, from an abuse on it</title>
            <author>Richardson, Richard, 1623?-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57240</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1396</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28478</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10603861</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10603861</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45370</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57240)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45370)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1408:53)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The substance of a letter occasioned by a discourse of the time called Christmas, from an abuse on it</title>
                  <author>Richardson, Richard, 1623?-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Richard Richardson.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by NUC pre 1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christmas.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45370:1"/>
            <head>The Subſtance of a LETTER, occaſioned by a Diſcourſe of the Time CALLED CHRISTMAS, From an ABUSE on it.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>L. N.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have in mind thy Friendly Viſit after our Dirty Abuſe and thy Admonition, ſeaſonable, as thou it may be thought'ſt for the future. But as for the Apoſtolical Tradition of <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> which thou ſaidſt thou hadſt read in ſeveral Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, I am ſo unſatisfied in it, that I have a Deſire to obtain the ſight of one of them: for I love to read a Piece that does ſay the utmoſt. 'Tis a Maxim, <hi>None would be Deceived.</hi> I am ſure I would not, and would not have others. I have read ſome of the moſt learned Antiquaries and Chronologers concerning it. Our Country-man <hi>J. Selden,</hi> ſpeaks as much for it, I think, as can be, in a Treatiſe of it under his Name, and more than may be, ſhewing more Reading than Ingenuouſneſs, or Ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs through Inconſiſtency (and ſo no Genuinneſs in the Treatiſe) obvious to a mean Underſtanding. For though ſuch Authors (Antiquaries) like Travailers, think they may Lye by Authority, becauſe few can contradict them; yet many may when they contradict themſelves, yea, almoſt any. For, own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>J. Selden</hi>'s Aſſertion in his Review, viz. That in the Eaſtern Church the Celebration of that Day was not received on the 25th of <hi>December,</hi> till the ancient Tradition of it was learned
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45370:2"/>from the Weſtern about four hundred years after Chriſt. This Treatiſe to vindicate him from inclining to the <hi>Puritan,</hi> reels quite over the <hi>Proteſtant;</hi> and for fear of the Brand of their hot Brain, as he ſaye, he leaps into the Purgatory of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of the inherent Holineſs of the Exact time, and that upon the Ground of unwritten Tradition; which he gives no Reaſon for not being firſt known in the Eaſtern Church, as well as the written; which Abſurdity implies a Contradiction. And he ſhews no Author in the firſt four hundred years before the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of it that mentions it: But <hi>Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> (where was a Patriarchal Church, being in the Eaſt, where the Church Cycles were kept, wherein there is no Rule for this Epicycle, nor gives this Treatiſe any, why it ſhould be retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade from <hi>Rome</hi> thither) he taxeth them of Curioſity that pretend to know either the Day, the Moneth or the Year of Chriſt's Birth, and ſpeaks of two Opinions about it, falling both in Summer Time. And this <hi>Clemens</hi> lived about Eighty Years after the Apoſtle time. If all the Eaſtern Churches had ſlept all that time, they would (as they Story of the Seven Sleepers) at their awaking have remembred ſurely, whether they had kept it in <hi>Summer</hi> or <hi>Winter;</hi> ſeeing the Tradition of it, which the later Fathers write of, was on the <hi>Winter Solſtice-Day,</hi> that is Two Weeks before the time wherein it is now obſerved; which is another Contradiction, to ſay, <hi>That the Exact time of the Birth only is ſacred,</hi> which was at the <hi>Solſtice;</hi> and yet ſay, <hi>That the Tradition of that Day, as it is now kept through all</hi> Chriſtendom, <hi>is both Apoſtolical and as Ancient as the Birth it ſelf:</hi> whereas the <hi>Julian</hi> and <hi>Gregorian</hi> Account of it differ Ten Dayes one from another, and both differ from the True Account according to <hi>Aſtronomy.</hi> Can all theſe three be the Exact Time, eſpecially ours of the <hi>Dionyſian</hi> Account, which makes (as <hi>Scaliger</hi> ſhews) the Birth of Chriſt to have been Two Years after <hi>Herod</hi>'s Death, who ſought his Life? Or can the very Name of the 25th of <hi>December,</hi> though not the Exact Time, make it ſacred by inherent Holineſs in the Time? He calls <hi>Cardan</hi> Impious for tying the Myſtery of the Sacred Time to the Rules of <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> and yet tying it himſelf to the Rules
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45370:2"/>of <hi>Aſtronomy</hi> (which he confeſſes Uncertain; another Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction) and to the Courſe of the Sun only, and not alſo of the Moon, as well as the Paſſion Day, about the Time of which all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> was in Broiles, and Excommunicating one another. Concerning which he ſaith, Peter, <hi>and</hi> James, <hi>and</hi> John <hi>teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at</hi> Alexandria, <hi>taught</hi> Mark, <hi>Biſhop there, the true Time of that Feaſt.</hi> Did the Apoſtles then conſpire to carry away the Tradition of the Birth Day ſo cloſely from <hi>Mark</hi> to <hi>Rome?</hi> Why! was it that <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor there ſhould teach <hi>Mark</hi>'s Succeſſor the Exact Time, four hundred years after, to ſhew the Pre-eminence of that Sea? Muſt that Feaſt alone be retrograde in their Divinity grounded on <hi>Aſtronomy?</hi> And was it Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and from the Birth it ſelf, before Apoſtles were, and before ſome of them were in being (a Miracle beyond the <hi>Papiſts</hi>) to confirm his <hi>Popiſh</hi> Tenet) Did his Brethren that deſpiſed him, the <hi>Carpenter,</hi> keep it from his Birth? or his Father repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and Mother, to whom he was obedient, keep it, contrary to their Fathers Examples, and their Account, after the Example of <hi>Herod</hi> the <hi>Idumean,</hi> and the <hi>Romans,</hi> and their Account (as it is now, and as he ſayes it was) who, as <hi>Polydore Virgil</hi> ſayes, received that Cuſtom from the <hi>Perſians</hi> of Obſerving Birth-dayes. As this man doth from the Example of thoſe that kept the Birth-dayes of <hi>Philoſophers, Princes</hi> and <hi>Heathen Gods,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Therfore he that ſcruples it to Chriſt, deſerves not the Name of a</hi> Chriſtian: But then he ſhould have ſhewn, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles got that Name upon that account, and that they ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Men to him alſo, as the <hi>Heathen</hi> did here in <hi>Brittain,</hi> and elſe-where, to their Gods, and what not; for one will follow as well as the other, from that Reaſon of his; and ſo did many things elſe, as <hi>Hoſpinian</hi> ſhews, who diſputes this Point largely againſt <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> which this man takes for granted, namely, the Sacredneſs of Times, not by Inſtitution, but of themſelves by Inherence, taking no notice of him (nor of the Anſwers of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to his Teſtimonies for unwritten Tradition) only he mentioning him amongſt thoſe Learned Men that oppoſe the Day, as <hi>Beroald, Paulus de Midleburgo, Suſliga, Joſ. Scaliger, Kepler, Wolphius, Lidiat, Calviſius, Caſaubon, &amp;c.</hi> But he
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45370:3"/>ſayes he did it according to Inſtructions: It ſeems he had not a mind to it, but as aforeſaid; for the Times turning, it lay by him Twenty Years, it may ſeem, when it ſhould in its way have informed Oppoſers (if ingenuous or genuine) and for any thing that appears by the Edition 1661. without his direction came out to countenance the Times, when it was like to be pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niary ſeven years after his Death, which Characters were uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally urged againſt Suppoſititious Pieces, as againſt the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Clement,</hi> &amp;c. There was ſomething in it alſo (increaſing the Suſpition) that he being a Lawyer, inclining to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates Power about Religion (with the <hi>Eraſtians</hi>) as appeared in his Hiſtory of Tythes, and the <hi>Aſſembly of Divines,</hi> ſhould yet here take the Plea of ſome Divines for the Sacredneſs of this, and glad of ſuch a Divinity that's but grounded on <hi>Aſtronomy.</hi> For he ſayes, <hi>That</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> Mark <hi>an Hundred Years after Chriſt's Birth, grew better Aſtronomers, and ſettled</hi> Eaſter. It is a Wonder then, they ſettled not this other too, but left it at ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to the Error of the Fathers (as he confeſſeth, becauſe, as he ſayes, they were no good <hi>Aſtronomers</hi>) and of all Chriſtian-Churches ever ſince, to Prophane the Exact Sacred Time, as he call, it, and all the immoveable Feaſts depending on it, after the Courſe of the Sun and Example of the <hi>Heathen.</hi> Theſe things and the Authorities he brings from <hi>Nicephorus Caliſtus,</hi> a Fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Author, <hi>Ann.</hi> 1300. and the <hi>Martyrology</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the <hi>Menology,</hi> which might ſuit the Time to the received Cuſtom then (as in the Chronicle of <hi>Alexandria</hi> the Tranſlator made the 21th of <hi>December</hi> the 25th, he ſayes) with other Suſpitious Teſt imonies of later Times, that he brings, are not ſufficient (to uſe his own Expreſſions) to inform a Judgment againſt the Silence or contrary Teſtimony of the firſt four hundred years (if the Queſtion depended there) <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> knowing nothing of that his only Inſtance of <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> ſo near him in place and time (which alſo contradicts his Aſſertion of the Eaſt not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it for four hundred years) nor the <hi>Armenians</hi> at this day, who keep it not yet, then knowing nothing of it, nor of <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi>'s Sermon about it. If the Exactneſs of <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions from <hi>Rome</hi> be credible (on which the main ſtrength
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45370:3"/>lies) that the very Day of <hi>Quirimus</hi> his Taxation in <hi>Jury</hi> was found in <hi>Rome</hi> to be on the <hi>Winter Solſtice Day,</hi> and the Year not found, as he proves, contradicting his Authorities out of Barbarous Tranſlations out of <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Africanus;</hi> its an Argument againſt it; ſeeing 'tis probable thereby, that the Tradition of the <hi>Solſtice Day</hi> ſprung from that (not being known before) the Taxation being then found, if truly delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to be about the <hi>Solſtice:</hi> As <hi>Caeſar</hi> deſign'd his two Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges into <hi>Brittain</hi> by the Equinox.</p>
            <p>I have been the longer on him, as being the only Man I have read of the inherent Holineſs of the Time, and Apoſtolical Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of it, that thou alledgedſt; and it may be the Author thou meaneſt, ſtiled, <hi>The Eminently Learned Antiquary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for thy other Allegation in thy <hi>Admonition,</hi> viz. <hi>That all</hi> ENGLAND <hi>keeps it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that reads the Church-Hiſtories, and minds the Effects of preſſing the National Worſhips, and the Sufferings that the ſincere Worſhippers, according to what was manifeſt to them, have undergone in all Ages, will think that alſo an inſufficient Argument, to inform the Judgment, or to quiet the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, by the ſubjecting it thereto. For beſides what the holy Scriptures record, of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> his preſſing his Religion he had deviſed, and caſting the three Children, for refuſing to ſubmit to it, into the Fiery Furnace: of the <hi>Perſians</hi> caſting <hi>Daniel</hi> into the Lyons Den, for ſerting his Window open, and praying to God, contrary to their Law, &amp;c. Other Hiſtories alſo relate how the <hi>Graciant</hi> forced their Worſhips on the <hi>Jews;</hi> as in the <hi>Maccabees</hi> the <hi>eruelty</hi> of <hi>Anticchus</hi> to them is notorious. After them the <hi>Romans</hi> preſſed theirs on the <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> who not being ſubject to them therein, were put to Death by them. And ſo was <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, who had tranſgreſſed his own Precept in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> chap. 13.1. <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the Higher Powers, &amp;c.</hi> (urged ſo often againſt us) if he had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood it in Religious Matters, that the <hi>Romans</hi> ſhould be ſubject to their Emperour therein; who on the contrary ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moſt Cruel Torments, rather than to condeſcend to Swear at
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45370:4"/>their Command, during three hundred years. Afterward the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (eſpecially the <hi>Arrians</hi>) perſecuted one another, for National Worſhips, as the Emperors came to be on their ſide. After them the <hi>Papiſts</hi> for many Ages. Then the <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> though about <hi>Anno</hi> 1548.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Magdeb.</hi> Abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by <hi>Oſian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> Hiſt. of Counc. of <hi>Trent,</hi> p. 295, 48, 387, 393.</note> in <hi>Germany</hi> a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil or Aſſembly of them there declared, <hi>That Ceremonies impoſed were bad, and they that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them were Cenſured:</hi> And before that had the Name of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> for proteſting againſt the Decree for <hi>Forcible Impoſing Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters concerning Religion:</hi> Yet afterwards the prevailing Party among them have Perſecuted the other about Conformity to their National Worſhips; and cauſed that none ſhould Buy nor Sell, but ſuch as had their Mark and their Name in the Forehead of their Profeſſion, and vailed Bonnet to their Maſs Times. Is not that an evident Mark of bowing to an Image of their own making? for Chriſt commanded no ſuch Image of him. <hi>Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinian</hi> ſayes,
<note place="margin">De Orig. Feſt. Ar. cap. 2.</note> This is attributed to Antichriſt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. as the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> to make Holy Days, one more than an another, in regard of the Myſtery. In this Particular, in his Treatiſe of the Birth Day of the Lord, he ſayes, He believes they inſtituted it in the Moneth of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> not becauſe they believed Chriſt was then born, but that they turned the Feaſts of their God <hi>Saturn</hi> into it, which were kept at <hi>Rome</hi> at that time; and he ſhews wherein Cuſtoms agreed that were obſerved in them both, in very many Reſpects. Here in <hi>England Polydore Virgil</hi> inſtances one of the Lords of Miſrule, uſed in thoſe Feaſts. Some ſay <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi>'s Feaſts were turned into it at <hi>York,</hi> therefore called <hi>Iule</hi> there. After which manner <hi>Hoſpinian</hi> ſhews very many Feaſt, in the Church came to be inſtituted. <hi>Nazianzen</hi> and <hi>Clarius Luithprandus</hi> ſhew the agreement of Riots in both Feaſts. <hi>Tertullian</hi> calls <hi>New-Years Gifts Saturn's (Saturnalitia)</hi> ſo doth <hi>Jerom.</hi> Green things were alſo uſed by the <hi>Heathen,</hi> and <hi>Miſſelto</hi> reverenced by the Prieſts here in <hi>Brittain,</hi> called <hi>Druides.</hi> The time of the bringing them in by Pope <hi>Leo</hi> and others, in condeſcending to the <hi>Heathen,</hi> is ſhewed in <hi>Piſgah Evangelica,</hi> namely, to ſuit
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45370:4"/>the <hi>Goths,</hi> and thoſe other Barbarous Nations in Religions, how he brought many things into the Church agreeable thereto, as had been done in ſeveral things at ſeveral times before. And muſt they not go out again, when they are diſcovered? Muſt <hi>Chriſtians</hi> be forced to keep up the Monuments of Idolatry and Superſtition in Goſpel Times? ſeeing the <hi>Jews</hi> in the time of the Law were commanded to deſtroy them, as in <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. and many other places. And the <hi>Galatians</hi> were ſuſpected for obſerving <hi>Dayes,</hi> and <hi>Times,</hi> and <hi>Moneths,</hi> and <hi>Years,</hi> which had been once indulged to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and ordained by God. And ſhould we be compelled to keep thoſe he never commanded? <hi>Socrates Eccleſ.</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. 5. c. 22.</note> who lived ſoon after the Stirs about keeping <hi>Eaſter,</hi> ſayes, <hi>Our Saviour and his Apoſtles never commanded his by any Law, as the Law of</hi> Moſes <hi>did, &amp;c.</hi> (<hi>Nicephorus</hi> alſo ſaith the ſame.)
<note place="margin">L. 12 c. 32.</note> But that <hi>Chriſtians</hi> drawn by a certain Cuſtom, by Tradition, becauſe they loved <hi>holy dayes to reſt from labours,</hi> as every one thought good celebrated the Paſſion. <hi>Jerom</hi> (on <hi>Gal.</hi>) to the Queſtion of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtivals,</hi> ſaith, <hi>All dayes are equal; and the holy day of the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is alwayes:</hi> and ſaith, <hi>He eats the Lord's Fleſh alwayes, &amp;c. Durandus</hi> ſaith (l. 6. c. 1.) <hi>More than Five Thouſand Feſtivals fall on every day through the whole year;</hi> ſo it ſhould be a continual Feaſt (as a good Conſcience is) if the Kingdom of God conſiſted in <hi>meat</hi> and <hi>drink,</hi> which the Apoſtle ſaith it doth not, but in <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Peace and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> I have read in ſeveral of the Fathers, as <hi>Chryſoſtom, Jerom, Theodoret, Euthymius, That God indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſeveral things to the</hi> Jews <hi>as to Children, to bring them off from Idols, and from performing them to Idols, as in this of Feaſts, becauſe they loved Belly-Chear; God ſuffered them to be done to himſelf, in their own reſpect, not his, who took no Pleaſure in them,</hi> Pſ. 50, &amp; 51. And on that of the Prophet, <hi>Spake I a word of Sacrifices, &amp;c. only obey my Voice. Rabanus</hi> &amp; <hi>Lyra</hi> note (on <hi>Jer.</hi> 7. &amp; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.) <hi>That Ordinances concerning ſuch things were not given till after they had worſhipped the Golden Calf</hi> [<hi>as they had learned of the</hi> Egyptians] <hi>and ſate down to eat and drink, and roſe up to play.</hi> But Chriſt put an end to ſuch things when the time was come that God ſought ſuch to worſhip him, as did it in Spirit and Truth, and not their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45370:5"/>own Bellies. He appointed no Worſhip then with <hi>Feaſting</hi> nor with <hi>Faſting.</hi> And as for the Types of the <hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> &amp;c. he fulfilled &amp; put an end to them, &amp; all that Prieſthood with its Rites. He commanded, to <hi>give to</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s, and to God the things that are God's.</hi> And he gave Tribute to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> though free, and his Apoſtle. Therein we have his Example too, as well as God's Command to the <hi>Jews</hi> to live quietly under <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar:</hi> But neither commanded to give to them the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour due to himſelf, to appoint his Worſhip for him. Muſt God be at Man's Courteſie, (CHRIST placed in their PANTHE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON) as thoſe called the Fathers reaſoned with them of old, who conſecrated them for Gods whom themſelves pleaſed, and appointed <hi>Feaſts</hi> and <hi>Temples</hi> for them? God appointed his own Worſhip in the Law, and left it not to Man to appoint it; much leſs in the Goſpel, when it is promiſed, <hi>Ye ſhall be all taught of God.</hi> And he appoints his own Miniſters, whom he pleaſeth, not Man. He ſaith, <hi>In vain do ye worſhip me, teaching for Doctrines the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions or Commands of Men.</hi> It hath been accounted a good <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> Plea, to argue from the Scripture negatively. There is no Command in the Scripture (nor Example, that I remember, beſides <hi>Herod</hi>'s) to keep a <hi>Birth-day;</hi> neither therein doth the Time thereof appear. Though ſome of the Ancients would ſeem to prove it from <hi>Luke</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 1 5. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 24 13.</note> upon miſtake of <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charias</hi>'s being High Prieſt (wherein the Uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the Teſtimony of the Fathers alone doth appear) who as <hi>Scaliger</hi> ſayes, concluded there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, againſt the Scriptures, that to be the time, from the High Prieſts time of burning Incenſe: whereas it appears plainly there, that <hi>Zacharias</hi> was of the 8th courſe, to burn Incenſe in his courſe, in the Temple only. And on that Error, <hi>Scaliger</hi> ſaith (whom the Learned call <hi>The great Critick of Times</hi>) <hi>depended the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the</hi> 25th <hi>of</hi> December, <hi>not before the year</hi> 400. But there's more ground or argument from <hi>Luke</hi> 1.26. that it was not at that time, but in <hi>Summer</hi> (or about the time of his Suffering) accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to what <hi>Clem. Alex.</hi> ſayes of the Eaſtern People, <hi>Aegyptians, Arabians, &amp;c.</hi> If the ſixth Moneth there ſpoken of, was the ſixth Moneth of the Year (as well as of <hi>Elizabeth</hi>) as the Language of the Scripture is, &amp; of the Fathers, according to the <hi>Jews</hi> reckoning.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45370:5"/>And the Rule in Interpretations is, according to Bp. <hi>Andrews</hi> (on <hi>Comm.</hi>) <hi>In ambiguis utrum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, Both Senſes to be taken when analogy of Faith will all on it,</hi> as it will here. And if thoſe that <hi>Clemens Alex.</hi> ſpeak of did conclude from hence, though uncertain, yet 'twas more ſafe, than for the other to conclude upon a certain falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: But that, as the Author excuſes it, <hi>The Fathers uſing the Scripture Language and</hi> Jews <hi>Manner in the numerical Title of the Moneths</hi> (as we do; wherein he has given us Authority from the Fathers as well as Scriptures, for naming the Moneths not after the <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> manner, and Names of their Gods) <hi>that they ſhould thereby miſtake the</hi> 9th <hi>moneth of the</hi> Egyptians <hi>for the</hi> 9th <hi>moneth of the</hi> Jews, is as credible as the other Miracles, &amp; that they ſhould miſtake <hi>Summer</hi> for <hi>Winter,</hi> as aforeſaid: and both are Arguments againſt the conſtant Tradition of it. Some will ſay, <hi>What a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs 'tis to keep a Day in Remembrance of Chriſt, without Scripture-proof!</hi> And we ſay, What a buſineſs they make of it, without Scripture (and therefore in Point of Worſhip, againſt it, according to the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as afore) ſo as to abuſe People about it, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of it. The <hi>Proteſtants</hi> at the <hi>Council of Baſil,</hi> maintained, <hi>That if Monkery was not of God, 'twas of the Devil</hi> (Comenius Schlavon. Hiſt.) ſo ſaid <hi>Luther</hi> of the <hi>Pope. And what a buſineſs,</hi> might ſome ſay, <hi>to bow the Knee to Chriſt's Image, to take his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> as they thought, <hi>in a Wafer Cake, in their Mouth!</hi> Were thoſe ſtubborn and wilful people, that would rather be burnt, than do it, in Q. <hi>Mary</hi>'s dayes? What a matter 'twas, thought the <hi>Greeks,</hi> for the <hi>Jews</hi> to take a piece of Fleſh in their Mouth, to eſcape Death, in the <hi>Maccabees:</hi> and for the Children in <hi>Daniel</hi> to ſeed of the King's Meat and Drink. The Commands of Men ſeem light to them that know not or regard not the Commands of God. But we ſay as the Apoſtles did, <hi>'Tis better to obey God than Man.</hi> Some will ſay, <hi>It gives Offence:</hi> ſo did the Preaching of the Croſs to <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile.</hi> Not to offend God is no Offence given to Man, but taken by Man. To have a Conſcience void of Offence towards God and Man was <hi>Paul</hi>'s Exerciſe, and ſo 'tis ours; yet he did not forbear to obey God, nor did the other Apoſtles; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Men took Offence at it, and thought they did God Service in Killing them: &amp; the <hi>Jews</hi> were mad againſt <hi>Paul</hi> for teaching the <hi>Gentiles</hi> not to obſerve their Law, though it was commanded
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45370:6"/>by God, as the Temple was, as theſe Traditions never were, but by the Pope, <hi>their Lord God,</hi> as the <hi>Canoniſts</hi> call him, which makes them ſo mad againſt us, as threatning to <hi>burn us.</hi> Never did <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> uſe to threaten, to <hi>burn Papiſts, for not keeping the Pope's holy dayes.</hi> Never were <hi>Sheep known to worry Wolves,</hi> who are diſtinguiſhed by their bloody Chaps, as <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> notes, though they may get on Sheeps Clothing: Chriſt gives a plainly diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing difference, <hi>By their Fruits ye ſhall know them,</hi> whether they be Thorns and Thiſtles, for they bear Prickles. Chriſt notes his Sheep by <hi>hearing his Voice:</hi> others hear only <hi>mens voices.</hi> And he ſays, <hi>They are a Little Flock:</hi> but the Nations and National Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers are Multitudes. <hi>All the World wonders after the Beaſt, and ſay, Who is able to contend with him, to diſobey him, or ſay, What doeſt thou?</hi> the ſpirit that rules in the Children of Diſobedience. But why may not we in this, as well as ſeveral famous learned of later times, who not only with the ancienteſt queſtioned it, but ſhewed their Opinions againſt it. <hi>Wolphius</hi> ſays, <hi>The Taxing was not likely to be in Winter, but Autumn,</hi> Dan. 9. <hi>In the midſt of the Week he made the Sacrifice to ceaſe,</hi> which ends in the moneth <hi>Niſan,</hi> the firſt moneth when he ſuffered: <hi>Wolphius</hi> proves the ſame by two Reaſons, <hi>He ended the Shadows at the time they began, namely, the</hi> Paſch, Pentecoſt, <hi>and that in the ſeventh moneth.</hi> 2dly, <hi>The</hi> Jews, ſays he, <hi>reckon he was born in ſuch a year, and in the beginning of it to be thirty years old at his Baptiſm. Midleburgenſis</hi> ſays, <hi>The World was created in the Spring Equinox, therefore it was meet the Reſtauration to be at that time reſumed. But,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hoſpinian, if thoſe men that were near that Age knew it not, why ſhould we believe</hi> Midleburgenſis, Epiphanius, <hi>or thoſe that ſtrive for</hi> December 25? And why ſhould we this Author? I have heard of ſome of late that have written of the <hi>Holineſs of Places</hi> alſo (but I have not ſeen any) and that an eminent Man in the Church ſhew'd ſigns of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to a Place where a Conſecrated Fabrick had anciently ſtood: As I remember I have read that <hi>Pauls</hi> in <hi>London</hi> was the Temple of <hi>Diana,</hi> and <hi>Peters</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> of <hi>Apollo,</hi> and ſo of ſeveral other Places. And the Author of the Hiſtory of the Church of <hi>Great Brittain, G. G.</hi> writes, <hi>That King</hi> Lucius <hi>here turned the Places of</hi> Arch Flamins <hi>of</hi> Heatheniſh <hi>Inſtitution into ſo many</hi> Arch-Biſhopricks, (as <hi>Pantheon</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> into <hi>All-Saints</hi> Church) <hi>and the Places of Twenty Eight</hi> Flamius, <hi>or</hi> Jupiter<hi>'s Prieſts, into
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45370:6"/>ſo many Biſhopricks; and turned the Temples builded for the worſhip of</hi> Pagan Gods, <hi>into Churches, for the Service of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>and that all the Poſſeſſions of the</hi> Heathen Flamins <hi>at</hi> Wincheſter, <hi>were conferred on</hi> Donatus <hi>the Biſhop and his Clergy there.</hi> And as I remember, Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> adviſed <hi>Auſtin</hi> to do the like among the <hi>Saxons.</hi> So here is a very ancient Tradition for their Holy Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Seeing then they have made men trucle to be their Drudges, Lackyes and Executioners for them and their Informers for their ſacred Revenue (as <hi>J. Selden</hi> calls <hi>Tythes,</hi> in his Hiſtory of them, yet there blaming them that made the <hi>divine right</hi> of them their Plea) to their Will-Worſhips (of whoſe Original much might be ſpoke too large for a <hi>Letter</hi>) and to their <hi>holy dayes</hi> and <hi>holy places,</hi> as hath been here ſaid. What remains, but that they proceed to their <hi>holy Garments</hi> (as Cardinal <hi>Woolſey</hi> made the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nobility bow to his Red Hat, ſo they) to their <hi>White Surplice,</hi> the Ornament, as Dr. <hi>Knewſtubbs</hi> ſaid, of the Prieſts of <hi>Iſis,</hi> the ancient <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Goddeſs, ancienter than the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> being in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> as ſome ſay, a very ancient Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and as old as that of their <hi>holy day;</hi> unleſs by <hi>Saturn</hi> be underſtood <hi>Moloch</hi> or <hi>Bell,</hi> the Son of <hi>Nimrod,</hi> the Nephew of <hi>Cham:</hi> an ancient Pedegree indeed of that Tradition; and as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient as any we read of, unleſs that <hi>Cain</hi>'s Offering, as ſome are of opinion, were <hi>Tythes</hi> or <hi>Firſt Fruits,</hi> as <hi>J. Selden</hi> writes in the beginning of his Hiſtory of them; and ſhews, that ſome have gone about to prove it from the Art <hi>Cabaliſtical</hi> in the like num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Letters of <hi>Firſt Fruits</hi> and <hi>Tythes:</hi> &amp; that is the higheſt we can go, or rather the loweſt in ferriting them in the Burrows &amp; Intrigues &amp; Labyrinths of their dark Traditions: and there we leave them, leſt we loſe ourſelves. What muſt they do that know nothing of Hiſtory, ſave the Scriptures (and ſcarce them) the good <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Plea? Muſt they by an implicit Faith believe as the Church believes, which they believe not to be the <hi>Church of God,</hi> not keeping the Commands of God written in the heart, <hi>to love God with all the heart, and their Neighbour as themſelves; to do as they would be done to, &amp;c.</hi> They that know nothing of Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory may juſtly ſuſpect, who was the Inſtituter of this Feaſt, by obſerving who are the moſt zealous for it and whoſe ſervice is done in it, Chriſt's or Antichriſt's. The Intereſt beſpeaks the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45370:7"/>Author. So that ſome, I remember, have written of it, <hi>That more ſolemn Service hath been done to Satan in the twelve days, than in the whole year beſides.</hi> If the Kingdom of God conſiſt in Meat or Drink, or in reſpect of a Holy Day, and mens <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> muſt be judged by that, we have <hi>Chriſtians</hi> by the Belly: And <hi>Bell</hi> muſt be a <hi>God,</hi> for being a <hi>Belly-God.</hi> But the Apoſtle's Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to the true <hi>Chriſtian-Romans</hi> was, <hi>Not in Gluttony and Drunkenneſs, not in Chambering and Wantonneſs, not in Strift and Envying; but put ye on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and make not provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the fleſh to fulfil the luſts of it: And whether ye eat or drink, or whatſoever ye do, let all be done to the Praiſe and Glory of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am thy Friend, and all mens in the Truth, <hi>Richard Richardſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>A few more Quotations for Confirmation of the fore-going.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Laertius in vita Plat. Plato</hi>'s Birth-day the ſame with <hi>Apollo</hi>'s, as this Author ſaith, was kept lately in <hi>Florence</hi> by the <hi>Medices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calend. vet. Rom a G. Hewart.</hi> Certain days for the Births of <hi>Mars, Apollo, Diana, Minerva,</hi> the <hi>Muſes, Hercules,</hi> and other Gods obſerved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>T. Langley's Abridgment</hi> of <hi>Polyd. Virgil,</hi> l. 6. c. 5. The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of keeping holy Birth-dayes, much uſed in <hi>Rome,</hi> though in <hi>Perſia</hi> firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ignatius</hi> 2 Epiſt. <hi>ad Magn.</hi> mentions only the Commemorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lord's Day, forbids to ſabbatize <hi>Jewiſhly</hi> but ſpiritually. He was the Diſciple of <hi>John.</hi> If that was not his, 'twas later.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſtine ad Januar.</hi> The Mercy of God would have the Church free. He lamented that in his time the Conditions of the <hi>Jews</hi> ſeemed more tolerable, ſubjected only to Legal Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, not Human Traditions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lib. Concord. cap.</hi> 14. At an Aſſembly of the Nobility and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> where three <hi>Electors</hi> were preſent, agreed, <hi>That all Ceremonies were left free.</hi> And denyed all that thought them either to be impoſed, or ſubmitted to, when impoſed, in condeſcenſion to Perſecutors.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:45370:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
